foreign
[Music]
from the studios of kpft in Houston
welcome to this week's edition of the
monitor my name is Mark badawi my
co-host is Emily Becker and we have a
guest guest and co-host I guess I was
going to say guest co-host but you're
both egberto Willis is joining us we're
going to be talking to him first instead
of the news headlines but let me just
give you a quick rundown of this week's
show because it's a little bit unusual
normally in the beginning we would be
doing news headlines but instead we're
going to be talking to Alberto so
welcome first of all well thank you for
having me sir how you doing today I'm
I'm good great I'm here
um we have two guests after that so uh
the usual format once the first segment
is over the first guest is John cariaku
he's a former CIA counterterrorism
officer and a former senior investigator
for the Senate Foreign Relations
Committee he's now a columnist for a
website called other words and we have a
link to his website and his latest
column which we'll be discussing with
him on the show this week it is called
let's talk about torture in which John
takes aim I think fairly squarely at
Bush era CIA directors George tenant
Peter Porter Goss and Michael Hayden and
several of their underlings who have
recently announced a plan to release a
book
predictably perhaps justifying torture
so we'll see what John thinks of that I
have an idea he might not like it our
second guest after the break uh will be
Steve horn he's the editor of D smog
blog and he recently wrote a piece
called Hillary Clinton State Department
emails Mexico energy reform and the
revolving door Steve will be our final
guest for the show so normally at this
point we'd be getting into news
headlines and I'd be reminding people to
go take a look at the website which they
still can do obviously and that is the
monitor.wordpress.com you can also go to
facebook.com monitor radio you can
follow me on Twitter at Market Valley
you can also follow all three of our
guests our first guest is egberto Willis
his Twitter handle is predictably Willis
egberto
um I had this idea that uh probably
somewhat similar to my experience with
kpft people have specific times of the
day or the week where they listen and
they may not be exposed to other shows
and they may not even know that your
show exists I suspect that there are
people who listen to your show that
don't know this show exists and so I'm
trying to cross-pollinate a little bit
so tell people about your show it's
Thursdays at three and it's called
politics done right what is what people
expect if they tune in if you too my
show is called politics done right and
it's on Thursdays at 3 P.M and what I do
is I try to engage the community it's a
and I don't and it's not only a local
show but it's a national show where we
actually try to get uh the the average
person in the body politics to engage
most people think that they cannot be a
part of politics I mean your show is is
excellent in in what I like to call the
Academia of politics what we try to do
at politics Done Right is bring it
closer to uh to folks who think they
don't have the ability or they were with
all to be a part of the body politics we
try to get them to engage and we also
try to get them to actually put their
voices out there and get their voices on
air because what I find is a lot of
times people have a lot to say but they
don't think they have the right to say
it or the Worth to say it it's a place
to say it or the place to say it exactly
exactly so what we're trying to do is
tell folks that you're part of America
and just like you can watch TV and see
all those pundits on you get your
opportunity to do that as well on
politics then right so it's a little bit
like a C-SPAN call-in show in that sense
there's a topic I guess for the week and
you have uh ideas that you want to get
through but you solicit opinion and
people call in right what I do is I I
generally start the show with something
I call the blog of the week and the blog
of the week is is some something that
that I research for quite a bit you know
most of the times it's something that's
happening and then we have a discussion
on the blog of the week now the thing
about it is what I call the show as well
as a people's show what that means is if
I may have an idea of what I want the
blog of the week to be but something may
be happening that people want to talk
about something else so we get we get
the meat of the blog of the week out of
the way and we either discuss it or
folks may call in and actually have the
subject change but it's their show so
they get the ability to they have the
ability to do that and it's it's every
Thursday and it's 3 P.M right every
Thursday at 3 P.M for one hour for one
hour okay so I guess one of the
questions I have with it being a call-in
show is do you have uh people who call
in all the time or do you have people
who you don't recognize like is it a
mixture
yeah it is a great mixture because what
you find is you have your your you have
your groupies right the folks that will
always call you every time that they can
but what I'm starting to find is that
the Surfers the radio Surfers are
starting to call as well and then
they're they're listeners that have been
that have been listening for quite a
while who hadn't had the courage to call
and they're suddenly with with the
constant trying to get people involved
they're getting up to speed or they're
getting the courage and they're calling
there's an interesting thing that
happened last time last Thursday
everybody who called were males
and I said look it's almost done with
the show and we haven't heard from a
woman yet
and at that point there were there's one
call on the line as soon as I said that
the whole thing lit up so it was it was
great because you felt that engagement
with the people that were you know were
actually listening to your show you know
uh before I started hosting this show I
used to do the boards the engineering
for uh saeed's show Arab voices and
there were people who would call in
every week right and there was also a
fairly short list of people who it
seemed would call in every every college
right and I was always a little bit
hesitant as to where they might take the
show or how they might derail the topic
because that show also had a guest right
so your show you don't have a guess it's
you and the listeners it's me and
listeners now every so often I bring
guests like uh going forward especially
since it's the election season I likely
have a whole lot of politicians in here
it in the studio but the idea is not
going to be the politician using the
show for a propaganda machine it's going
to be I'll talk to the politician for a
little bit and then let the people talk
to the politician and you know for me
it's going to be always
the folks out there and that's going to
be leading the show so this brings up
another question and it's something that
I wrestle with every election season and
that is that the Federal Election
Commission has rules about uh so-called
fair play or equal air time or you know
which on TV was a doctrine that was
undone by Reagan Reagan yes
um so how do you deal with elections and
either expressing or not expressing your
own opinion and and staying within the
rules but also being honest with your
audience well my audience know that I am
a left-wing liberal I tell them that
almost every single session I also tell
folks that the intent of my show is not
to listen to only left-wing liberals I
want everybody on my show so I encourage
Republicans anarchists Communists
socialists libertarian Libertarians
right everybody to come on the show and
you know what sometimes I get them so I
mean the idea is that um I am not shy
about what my political affiliation is
I'm not shy about where I stand from a
political standpoint but what I try to
do is say this is community radio and I
want to hear you know everybody's point
of view and I really don't have a you
know a problem to have folks call in and
talk because I'm with another group
called The Coffee Party USA and one of
the things that we try to do is
introduce dialogue into um into our
system because there's too much as you
know if you the rush limbaughs and the
Hannity so my show is nothing like that
I don't care where you come from you'd
always first of all as the host I'm
always extremely respectful to anybody
who calls in no matter what tone they
use when they call in and generally even
those that call in very wild with a wild
tone ready to have my head on a platter
by the time the conversation ends you
know whether we agree or disagree we
have a conversation well that's
important and Emily I don't want to hog
the conversation so jump jump in if you
have if you have questions as well
um so I guess the the other the other
concern that I have about Collins and I
sort of alluded to it is that sometimes
people can call in and completely change
subject yes with this show sometimes
when you know technical issues have led
to guests not being available or phone
phone lines have had a problem or
something we'll open the lines but I've
always been very impressed with the
quality of phone calls that we get and I
don't know if if
okay sort of I guess in some way
undermines an assumption that a lot of
media has that topics are too
complicated that we can't really get
into this that you know people don't
understand I think that it does and I
don't know if you would just would agree
with you know I know uh Royal Muhammad
for example says the people are smarter
than you think it's too I think it's two
answers right one is here the people are
smarter than we think many times but the
second one is you the quality of your
show determines a lot of times your
listenership okay so I mean if you have
a good quality show of which you have
like I tell folks all the time I like
I'm an engineer by training okay so and
there are scientists in the broadcast
type business somebody like yourself and
Emily who are in the school system and
the the university system and the PHD
levels and all that kind of stuff you
are the scientists of the of the media
you know of the media domain there are
others in the media domain that they are
the the populist I consider myself the
populist in the in the media domain and
you need I think you need both sides so
whereas some programs do well to have
people calling or would be best based on
people calling in I don't think all of
them should be that way because as an
example when I talk about your show when
I'm coming into the to the show before
and listening to your show one of the
things that I like is the level of
complexity that you can get out of a a
guess then somebody like me the engineer
who is the populist can actually break
that down in in a certain way to the
people at law large so I think both of
them are needed you know I think both
both styles are actually needed for for
that type of interaction with the public
at large okay well I I have tuned in and
I encourage people to do so the show is
called politics Done Right the host is
egberto Willis he's joining us this
weekend is actually going to be staying
with us for the remainder of the show so
you might hear him piping with questions
for either of our guests uh John kariaku
up next and Steve horn second guest uh
Thursdays at three egbertoni any final
closing sentiments for people before we
uh sort of let you go although you're
staying right yeah please I tune into
the show and call into the show and
actually make sure to go
kpft has a whole lot of good talk shows
interspace with the other good
programming that we have look them up
and and and listen to them all and I
should point out that this show is
carried by several other stations around
the country at different times of the
week and so people might be listening in
not on a Monday and wondering if they
can hear your show and call in as well
and they can you can listen to kpft
streaming on the internet right from
anywhere in the world obviously and if
you're willing to pay for the long
distance phone call then you can call
the Station during Alberto's show and
that number is the usual number that
everyone in kpft land knows
713-526-5738 of course and now you can
call in and have your say so we
encourage you to do that thank you very
much well our engineer Robert Gartner
has our first guest on hold already so I
think we'll go to a very short musical
break and uh we'll be right back with
John cariako stay tuned
foreign
welcome back to the monitor my name is
Mark bavali my co-host is Emily Becker
and our guest and guest co-host is
egberto Willis who's joining us just for
this week's show our first guest uh I
guess second guess really would be John
cariankou John welcome back thanks for
having me again it's good to have you
back on uh John is
um no stranger to this show I think
Johnny did the first interview after the
restrictions were placed on You by the
Department of Justice after you are
finally able to speak so it was a
pleasure and a privilege to have you on
for that thank you for people who
haven't heard of you John is a former
CIA accounts terrorism officer a former
senior investigator for the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee and the only
person
um in what I think is a travesty really
to serve any jail time in anything
connected with torture and and not
because John was involved in the torture
but because he blew the whistle on it
John is now columnist with other words
and we have a link to his latest piece
on there called let's talk about torture
uh John you take a pretty Square aim at
several of the Bush era CA directors
notably Georgetown Porter Goss and
Michael Hayden who are planning now to
release a book tell people what this
book is going to be about and what your
issues are with those people and what's
going to be in their book yes these
these three former CIA directors that
you mentioned George Tenet Porter Goss
and Michael Hayden and five other Bush
era senior Cia officers everybody from
from Mike Morrell and John McLaughlin to
Jose Rodriguez and Philip Mudd a former
general counsel of the CIA John Rizzo
they they all wrote this book together
that takes aim at the Senate torch
report and really to make a long story
short it it tries to justify the torture
program it tries to argue that torture
worked that torture was moral and that
it saved American lives and I thought
there was no sense in pulling any
punches
the big lie that they have tried to uh
to uh
portrait and to perpetuate since they
left office
I was going to call it what it was and I
wrote this column for otherwords.org and
so for people who haven't had a chance
to to read that and we met we went over
some of these arguments before and I've
discussed them at length with various
people in the intelligence Community uh
and and the legal Community about the
efficacy and legality or illegality of
torture just uh from your experience in
the CIA and in the intelligence world
tell people what the issues are with
torture I mean we we see uh TV shows
like uh 24 and various other things that
seem to show that uh you know if you if
you lean on someone hard enough they'll
tell you exactly what you need to know
and it'll be reliable and dependable and
truthful
so simple the the truth is and
psychiatrists and psychologists have
argued this for many many years torture
doesn't work torture never works the
person being tortured simply will tell
his torturer what he thinks that person
wants to hear just to make the torture
stop
one thing that many Americans forget
is that the documents that the that the
Senate select committee on intelligence
used to write the torture report were
primary source documents these were
contemporaneously written CIA documents
from the field to CIA headquarters as
the torture program was taking place so
we know firsthand that the torture did
not work that the torture did not result
in any actionable intelligence no
attacks were disrupted and no American
lives were saved
then you're comfortable stating that
categorically categorically there is
absolutely no truth to this contention
by George Tennant and the others that
torture worked never mind the argument
that it was illegal you know the United
States is signatory to a number of
international treaties and conventions
most specifically the United Nations uh
convention Against torture which
specifically for
uh
that the CIA was using in its secret
prisons overseas
it's so distressing to me uh and I you
know I hesitate to say this while you're
on the air with us because in a way
you're the only person who paid the most
direct price other than of course the
people who are tortured but you're the
only uh intelligence uh analyst official
CIA employee or contractor who's served
time in prison for torture but not for
actually torturing I mean what what sort
of response did you get when you were
still in the CIA and when you tried to
blow the whistle internally about this
what did people in official them say to
you uh are you were you just a
troublemaker or did they try and argue
the points with you or what was that one
senior officer that I had to put that I
had displayed what he called a shocking
lack of commitment to counter-terrorism
that was the first time anybody
criticized me on this issue it was a
shocking lack of commitment to
counterterrorism and then I I sort of
became known as the human rights guy
and uh and people stopped asking me
things related to torture to
interrogation nobody asked my opinion
after a while and that was perfectly
fine but one of the things that that was
very disappointing to me was that no one
else came forward not after I went on
ABC News in 2007 and said that the CIA
was torturing its prisoners not after
the Senate torture report was released
so we know now from that torture report
that there were CIA officers in the
field who were writing back to
headquarters and saying this is wrong
it's torture I don't want to have any
any role in it but they've never gone
public and they've never said anything
about what led to their decision to walk
away from the torture program and do you
very disappointing how many of those
people do you think had the opportunity
to come forward before you you went
public and then we can talk about why
they might not have done after you went
public because the lesson's there for
them I think are pretty pretty obvious
2002 to 2005. so we're talking about at
least two or two and a half years where
someone could have come forward and
could have said something and we knew
that there was torture taking place
because there had been leaks to Human
Rights Watch there's been leaks to
Amnesty International and even the
international Committee of the Red Cross
had written an internal report saying
the CIA was torturing its prisoners so
we we know that that somebody was
talking at some point but not not to the
media necessarily no not to the media
okay so I mean I guess after you came
forward and people saw what happened to
you the way the administration went
after you and this didn't just end
obviously with the Bush Administration
the Obama Administration continued the
same fight
um what is your take on
I mean I guess the obvious motivation
for these uh CIA directors and their
underlings as you put it uh trying to
justify torture and claiming not only
that they had the legal Authority but
that it was effective they're obvious
political motivations for that uh what
are the other motivations absolutely I
think this is
when it comes right down to it the
torture program is their legacy when
their obituaries are written it's going
to mention that they were the creators
and the implementers of the torture
program and they want to repeat this lie
that torture worked over and over and
over again
American people are so stupid
it's really about their their place in
history and their personal legacies and
there's also the issue of patriotism
right I mean uh the idea that if you
question anything the administration
does whatever the administration might
be uh to use George Bush's words that
you're either with us or you're against
us so any dissent means you're on the
side of terrorism yes um you know this
is something that I've argued since I
was a teenager progressives are
progressives are patriots too you don't
have to to out Hawk the hawk in order to
prove your patriotism it's patriotic to
Stand Up Against torture it's patriotic
to want our country to uh to respect its
International uh agreements and and
treaties
so you said that you were accused of uh
lack of commitment to counter-terrorism
uh one of the things that I've said on
this show multiple times uh various
opportunities that I've had when this
topic comes up is the torture along with
uh you know the invasion of Iraq and
Afghanistan and the Drone program
actually creates cancer creates
terrorism uh did you ever have a
response to these people that actually
were creating more terrorism with this
torture yeah
the agency including several senior
level officers
I think that it's a it's a proven fact
that some of these programs create new
terrorists I I've
interviewed or interrogated
myself uh young Al-Qaeda fighters who
had no problem with the United States
had no intention of taking up arms until
a drone flew over their Village and
killed their you know cousin or brother
or fill in the blank with a family
member
um it's it's these it's these attacks
that anger whole you know segments of
the populace and uh and that that really
bucked people up who uh decide then to
go to Afghanistan or to Iraq or to
wherever to make Jihad against the
Americans so uh how do you convince
people who and I'm one of them who would
think that uh you know the CIA torture
program which I guess officially existed
from 2002 and and we're told is now
officially over that in fact it still
goes on that Renditions probably still
has happened that black sites still
exist that there are still people in
Guantanamo and other places who are
likely being mistreated what what do you
say to to that to rather cynical
position I would say that I would not
bet money that the that the torture
program has gone away uh look nobody has
said anything about banning Renditions
right the Renditions can be an
absolutely horrible thing that lead to
torture but even the Senate torture
report hasn't uh addressed Renditions so
I would guess that Renditions are still
taking place now the CIA lies about just
about everything well that wouldn't that
shouldn't surprise anybody right right
it shouldn't surprise anybody they lied
to the Senate investigators they they
tapped the Senate investigators phones
and um and uh
uh spied on the on the um
sorry my son just walked down the steps
and I lost my train of thought but
anyway over the years had they
interferred with the computers as well
right overstay committees
I mean how do we know that there are no
more black sites what about the new
prison that was built at Bagram air base
is that ours or is it the Afghans who's
being held in it and do they have access
to the Red Cross I don't think those
those questions have been answered right
egberto I think wants to jump in yeah I
have a question and it goes as follows
first you said that torture does not
work do you think these guys believe
that it works or do you think there's
some ulterior motive that they're
actually uh still with the torture
program or still you know doing
Renditions Etc
reputation that it doesn't work but I
think that they think that they made a
decision they have to stick with that
decision they have to justify the
decision and they're going to go to
their graves uh arguing for it
so I think again it's it's a legacy
issue I wanted to is it that or do you
think it could be more Sinister that
what we really need to ensure is that we
in fact have conflict throughout the
world at all the time well that I I
agree with you with you know if there's
no conflict if there's no war then the
military-industrial uh complex makes no
money there's no work for this gigantic
bureaucracy that the CIA and NSA and
Associated agencies have become what do
you do with all those people those
people only work and only prosper and
only Thrive when there's a war to fight
exactly that's I mean that's it gets
that gets to the heart of of one of the
sort of ongoing themes of this show and
that is uh you know trying to solve
problems by following the same failed
methods uh should not surprise anyone
that continues to produce the same
outcomes uh someone at some point said
that was the definition of insanity
Insanity um May I add something yeah
please do we should be just as angry
with the Congressional oversight
committees as we are with anybody else
that's involved in this because these
oversight committees not only are
briefed fully briefed on all of these
programs but they're the ones who go to
the Appropriations Committee and argue
for their funding and you know the the
Frank churches of the world are gone it
seems like there you can only choose for
a committee membership between
neoconservatives and neoliberals and
they're both going to get us into the
same mess
and there's there's really no adult
supervision on Capitol Hill so so John
when you joined the CIA what was your
motivation initially what did you
discover when you spent time there and
what would you say to someone today who
might be thinking about that kind of
career path
I've I've forbidden my children I have
five children I have forbidden them from
ever applying to the CIA to the FBI or
to the NSA
um I joined the CIA in January of 1990.
I was recruited in graduate school to
work in the cia's directorate of
intelligence that's the analytic arm
and that was a period of time a period
that lasted from from the church
committee hearings in 1976 until really
until September 11th where there was a
there was a hard and fast rule that the
CIA whether it liked it or not had to
respect human rights and as a result on
the operations side
uh our operators were not allowed to
recruit any potential sources who had
human rights abuses in their own past
now I thought that was laudable as Ezra
we didn't get a lot of the
we otherwise
so I was very idealistic I came from an
immigrant household
and my grandfather kept a picture of
Franklin Roosevelt on the top of the
television all my life
and he instilled in my brother and
sister in me the idea that
the country was so kind to us to let us
in when we needed help the most at the
height of the Great Depression that we
needed to do something across the
generations to pay back that hospitality
and that thing was public service
he always urged me to go into public
service and so when I was in grad school
and uh and my graduate school advisor
approached me
about working for the CIA I thought wow
great not only what will it be
interesting and I'll get to see the
world but I'll get to pay that back to
the country that's been so good to us
and so I I gladly went into the CIA
it was only
I'm gonna say eight years later when I
told my boss that I was going to switch
over to operations and he pulled me
aside and he said you know they kill
people over there and I said oh come on
you watch too many movies he said no I'm
serious they kill people over there
and I said well that's you know that's
not me I'm not
it's not my thing and it wasn't really
until September 11th that I realized
they really do kill a lot of people over
there
and over there you mean the operations
side instead of the operating the
analytical side correct so I guess if
you're if you're still driven I don't
mean you individually but anyone who
might be still be driven by uh this this
idea of public service and of repaying
the country for whatever they think the
country has done for them
and you're telling people that you
wouldn't tell you would forbid
explicitly forbid your children from
joining the CIA what other alternatives
are there well you know
there are things like this is going to
sound maybe like a little bit of a
cliche but but there's the Peace Corps
and there's the Foreign Service uh you
know the U.S information service there's
a lot that you can
you can do you know
serve your country and promote
American ideals that we all like to
think we have
um but I think that our intelligence
services are out of control and that's
not one of them now I used to believe
that
um the only way to change the CIA was
from the inside that the CIA is a
permanent permanent organization a
permanent structure bureaucratic
structure and the only way to change it
is from the inside I I'm not sure I
believe that anymore you know Daniel
Patrick Moynihan wrote a book in 1976 in
which he advocated for the for the
breakup of the CIA and and people mocked
him you know on Capitol Hill and off but
we know now also that John Kennedy
wanted to break up the CIA and I think
that uh you know this is probably
something we should be debating
and it's not uh it's nice it's not even
a conversation
is there a reason for
a seat called defense Human Services uh
certainly analysis can be done either at
DIA or at the state Department's Bureau
of intelligence and research
the cia's Science and Technology
directorate can be spread over a number
of you know more than a dozen government
agencies so do we really need a CIA I
think no not anymore
seems like that what we're looking at is
as governments sort of Feed in on itself
you know I I don't know that a president
has the courage or any president would
have the courage to actually shut down
the CIA or any one of those
organizations especially in these times
where most Americans are freaked out
about this great terrorist nun threat
that we actually are looking at I think
you're right and that's the problem
well so so John uh and this might be the
last question we have because we're
going to run out of time here in a few
minutes but given the current situation
in Iraq and Syria and the rise of Isis
or isil or daesh or whatever you want to
whatever name you want to give that
group what is the role of intelligence
and if you had the ear of either this
president or whoever the incoming
president was going to be what would you
suggest would be an appropriate policy
to to deal with the crisis over there
I know that's a huge question which is
why I'm giving you I'm giving you a few
minutes the first thing I would do
literally the first thing I would do
would be to cut off arm sales to the
entire region because the arms always
end up in either the wrong hands or they
corrupt the people with the right hands
and you know you look at these you look
at the weapons that Isis has and they're
American weapons and they're the same
weapons that the Iraqi government had
before
uh at the same time
let's let's
face the facts the United States created
Isis in a backhanded way certainly you
know by by allowing
by allowing these human rights abuses to
fester in places like Abu ghraib or
arasheed in Iraq uh but we know that
isis's leaders came out of an American
Military prison in central Iraq so cut
off the arms respect human rights close
down these prisons no matter where they
are
start treating people with uh with
dignity
and how much of this would translate
into the a post-cold war framework that
I feel like a lot of policy makers and
intelligence people haven't quite
grasped yet it used to be the case
during the Cold War that there was a
belief not only in the state department
but in the intelligence Community as
well that it was kind of a zero-sum game
and whatever means you had at your
disposal you would follow so that the
Soviet Union wouldn't capture the
influence of whatever that Regional
country or or you know system might be
well now the Cold War is Over right at
least so we're told but we haven't
really changed uh the the positioning of
anything it doesn't so we haven't and
you know I still have a lot of friends
in the CIA with whom I speak and um all
they talk about these days is Russia
Russia Russia Russia is the enemy Russia
is the big problem we have to be worried
about the Russians and I disagree with
that completely I really do I think
we've dropped the ball
on relations with the Russians I'm no
Vladimir Putin fan certainly uh he's a
former KGB Colonel but uh I think that
we have more we have more Avenues
on which we can work with the Russians
then we do problems with the Russians
and if we could settle our differences
with the Russians I think it would make
the rest of the world an awful lot
easier and there would be that peace
dividend that we never got there would
be you know I remember complaining
plane worked so hard to not exercise
diplomacy as George W Bush's state
department and Barack Obama for all his
faults and believe me I'm no Barack
Obama fan
with Iran and he's done the right thing
with Cuba and uh we need the right thing
to be done with the Russians as well but
is he is he doing the right thing with
uh the Iraq Syria situation I I don't
think so no I mean just sending sending
arms to you know a group of doctors and
engineers and and people who we don't
even really know they are is not going
to settle the case the truth is we have
two bad choices we have Bashar al-assad
and we have Isis we're going to have to
figure it out we're gonna have to work
with the Iranians you know on the one
hand and uh and work with the Iraqis on
the other well one another perspective
John would be that we shouldn't really
feel like we have a choice we should
just get out of it and let the locals
handle it for themselves no yes
well you know I I would hate to just
abandon so many Innocents there the
Kurds desperately need some help even if
it's just medicine and food Aid the
yazidis are still being just tormented
mercilessly by ISIS so for human rights
reasons I I would like to at least have
a humanitarian presence yeah I don't
think I disagree with that I don't think
that food Aid or you know shelter or
even a no-fly zone that doesn't drop
bombs on Villages I don't have a problem
with that either but you know expanding
drone strikes and sending weaponry and
and funds and that's that's not going to
work no that's not going to work it's
never worked in the past there's no
reason to think it would work now well
um John I'm afraid about that time but I
really appreciate you being with us and
I really encourage people to read your
new column at other words it's called
let's talk about torture we have a link
to it from our website but you can also
go to otherwords.org let's talk about
torture John cariaku former CIA Council
terrorism officer former senior
investigator for the sound Foreign
Relations Committee thanks so much for
joining us thanks for having me great to
be with you thank you uh we'll take a
brief break and we'll be right back with
Steve horn stay tuned
[Music]
welcome back to the monitor my name is
Mark Ravalli my co-host is Emily Becker
and our guest and guest host is egberto
Willis joining us for this final segment
of the show our guest for the remainder
of the show is Steve horn Steve welcome
good to be here thanks for having me
it's good to have you on Steve is the
editor of uh D smog blog he recently
wrote a piece we have a link to from our
website called exclusive Hillary Clinton
State Department emails Mexico energy
reform and the revolving door uh Steve
it's your first time on the show so I
know you you may not be familiar with
the format but uh the aim of the show
really is for me to ask one question and
get out of the way and give you as much
time as possible to explain the story so
tell people who haven't read your column
yet what it is you found what connects
the state department emails with Mexico
energy reform and what is this revolving
door
absolutely well you know this story came
about it was something I was working for
a while so it wasn't something that only
came from the Hillary Clinton emails the
Hillary Clinton emails himself so she
gave me
um sort of a a good news hook for it
let's say because those are already
pretty controversial thing uh because of
the basis of the emails that is that
there were emails stored on her own uh
private server and her own private email
address so she was doing the State
Department business on which I think a
lot of critics think you know first of
all applies in the face of the Freedom
of Information Act second of all uh
flies in the face of national uh
archives acts in terms of terms of uh
you know what we'll have to the emails
when she's done the state department so
these emails have slowly come out after
a lawsuit that was filed by Jason
Leopold at Vice news who's an
investigative reporter there and the
state department is now putting these
out once a month at the end of every
month so a listeners can expect another
a patch to come out at the end of August
but so in both batches there have been
some really interesting little tidbits
and details about something that I
followed closely for a long time as well
and that is uh the International Energy
coordinator positioning at the state
department and what that International
Energy coordinator was tasked with and
one of the things that I've been
following also is something called the
global Shale gas initiative it's now
called the unconventional gas technical
engagement program and
basically um the the role of this the
person that was doing this job the first
person ever to do it was David Goldwin
I'll talk about a little bit uh soon and
this is Steve sorry this is a state
department position right correct okay
State Department's position that was
actually originally created under
President uh George W bush but it was
only really active at that time as far
as I could find in my research on stuff
pertaining to
biofuels in Brazil and so it wasn't very
active on the oil and gas issues didn't
become very active on those issues until
Hillary Clinton's State Department
during the first term of President Obama
and still active in those areas today so
much so that they've even created a
whole Bureau in the state department
called The Bureau of energy resources
and so that's sort of the big picture
here and so in those emails you can see
that um a little bit of detail about uh
how that position was created and who
was first hired and also a description
of that position and with one caveat and
the caveat is that the entire job
description this was the basis for
another article I wrote is redacted so
we don't know how the state department
was actually describing the person that
would show his position to potential
applicants but a long story short there
is that David Goldwyn assumed the
position and you could see some chatter
about that in the Hillary Clinton emails
in the second batch that basically my
article is about and so going to that
and that gets into the revolving door
story
um you can see that in the emails one of
the main things that David Goldman would
be working on is energy reform in Mexico
when my when I say reform I mean the
privatization of Mexico's energy sector
especially in oil gas and electricity I
don't really know how much coal Mexico
has but I think that most of the stuff
I've been reading shows this is
pertaining to oil and gas and
electricity and so this is interesting
uh before we get to some of the details
it's interesting that reform quite often
takes on that meaning you know when the
IMF is restructuring loans when the
World Bank is is tying strings to their
loans they quite often discuss reform
and invariably what that means is
privatization it doesn't tend to mean
almost anything else as far as I can
tell right and so I use the term reform
America just because that's what powers
the peacock it is privatization of the
entire sector so that came about in
December 2013 and what wasn't really
there wasn't really well understood is
the role of the United States government
played what what does these emails show
and then further research uh into
looking at the Wikileaks cables um it's
very clear that the United States
government in particular
um David Goldwyn who was International
Energy coordinator and also uh the the
ambassador of the Mexico uh under
Hillary Clinton uh early on in her
10-year Carlos basketball those two were
very active on this issue between 2009
and
2013 and so sort of halfway between
Hillary Clinton's tenure at the state
department David Goldwyn steps down from
the International engine Clinic position
and Carlos Pascual who was the U.S
ambassador in Mexico he becomes the
International Energy coordinator but
what's sort of what state what remains
is that both of them were pushing behind
and I said behind the scenes because
this was if you look at the Wikileaks
cables you can see that they purposely
kept this behind the scenes definitely
in Mexico and probably even in the
United States because there's a lot of
opposition to fracking a lot of
opposition too uh is this new technology
on both sides of the board I didn't want
to be known the United States was
involved so in the weekly cables they
said you know we need to be involved in
this is very important but we cannot be
linked to it at all has to be completely
off the books and so you know what the
cable shows they were very involved in
it and
um I guess the revolving door part of it
you know to get to that part is that um
Baldwin and um basketball neither of
them work at the state department
anymore they both left after Hillary
Clinton's tenure at the state department
gold went halfway through Pascual a
little bit in to carry senior but he
hasn't really worked much under John
Kerry they both left and went to the
private sector and both of them are now
doing work pertaining to
Mexico or work at firms that do stuff
pertaining to Mexico so in the case of
Pasquale he
uh works at a firm called IHS Inc which
has an entire portfolio connected to
energy in Mexico and they're a
consulting firm that does studies and
that sort of thing that are basically
entirely funded by the oil and gas
industry and often
these are part of the kind of the think
tank Echo chamber interestingly they're
probably actually a for-profit
consultancy on like the firms that
Goldwyn affiliate is affiliated with
like Atlantic Council like Brookings
institution and like I mean he also has
a for-profit consulting firm called
Golden Global strategies so Goldwyn is
author of lots of these types of reports
that are pro privatization of Mexico's
energy sector and one interesting note
about Goldwyn
um there's days literally like a week
after uh Mexico's energy privatization
passed in Mexico's
um legislature and then when the
president after the president signed it
into law Pena Nieto uh just about a week
after that through the Atlanta Council
he released a report talking about he
knew like all the details of the
legislation he and wrote a long report
about it which just to me that wasn't
actually part of my article but uh to me
that kind of shows that he definitely
had a lot quite a bit of behind the
scenes knowledge of intimate details of
the policy and shows that he you know he
was he's been a key actor on this for a
long time and then and then you're
referring to here is Godwin or Pasqual
Goldwyn okay yeah so gold one here I
mean if and there'll be one more figure
I want to talk about his name is Neil
Brown but Baldwin to talk about him for
a second
um first of all I think golden is
probably the most important figure in
the story of the Three that I covered in
terms of evolving door in terms of and
that that's because he's a guy who's
been into and out of the revolving door
private sector public sector you know a
couple times he used to actually work
for the original Clinton administration
doing energy related stuff then he went
back then he went to his uh consulting
firm he's also affiliated with a law
firm
um called Sutherland which does uh legal
stuff pertaining to these same issues
and so he sells council at that firm the
Goldman's also uh I just want to
highlight he's a key he's a protagonist
in the book by Ken Silverstein called
The Secret World of Royal and in that
book by 10 Silverstein refers to him as
quote unquote a fixer so what what
Golden's done through his basically his
entire career Mexico is just one example
he's been a guy who goes into countries
with tough situations and attempts to
open up basically open up markets for uh
you know internet and basically U.S oil
and gas firms like Chevron like Exxon
Mobil and so he's had a whole career of
this and that's highlighted pretty
extensive income silver scenes but I
would say that Mexico is one of the
latest chapters of things that he's done
but he's he's not a well-known figure
per se but he's a very powerful figure
in Washington DC and so so before we get
to uh before we get to Neil Brown
um I just want to spell out some of
these details here because I think that
it's possibly some listeners may have
missed some of the big plot which is the
the state-owned oil and gas company in
Mexico pemex I I don't know if I'm
saying that right
um they they were broken up essentially
through a law passed in Mexico and
signed by president pininato
and you're and you're saying in your
story that uh Goldwyn and Pasqual and
and Neil Brown to some extent as well
were heavily involved in creating that
law
correct at least in terms of the
influence of things that they did create
an atmosphere in which uh the passage of
this reform
was possible so so when when Chemex was
broken up what who who bought which
chunks of it and and what happened now
to Mexico's oil and gas former State
Monopoly yeah that's a good question
mostly what happens now is that Timex
can more easily do joint ventures with
other companies for exploration and
production and Drilling and so and many
of these companies presumably would be
foreign owned including American
correct yeah and so you can already see
it in the first uh there's there's been
one bit so far there weren't as many
bids as uh observers thought there would
be but uh you know there's been some
shallow water uh deeper uh offshore
drilling it's uh and uh you know the
companies are from the United States and
so so I guess the reason I bring that up
is that uh you know some people would
say but possibly and you know if you
don't know enough about this story or
some of the other stories like you know
private medical health insurance or a
big farmer or whatever you might say
well you know people like Neil Brown and
Pasquale and David Goldwyn well they
know the industry they know how things
run and it's perfectly okay for them to
go from private to public sector like
this because they they know how to make
things happen right uh what's what's
your response to that
well you know I I would I would say that
I'd have two responses one is that this
is a particular industry oil and gas
industry that
um you know it's not you know I wouldn't
say it's akin to other Industries in
that maybe in some ways it is but I
think that uh you know the actions of it
are leading to catastrophic climate
change there's no denial that the the
consumption and production and
and all that all the stuff I was doing
fossil fuels that are leading to climate
change so their actions are actually
hurting the entire planet first of all
but second of all there's just a
stuff that's fracking itself and all the
documented stuff that has to do with
water contamination and
air pollution in communities and so
they're at you know they they very they
do know this area very well and actually
their studies are
um sometimes interesting this may have
well documented but their actions are
actually leading to
extreme harms and so I think that that's
important detail to keep in mind and
then it's also I think it's just
yes they do know the area well but it's
it's very clear that they traded a their
government access the private sector let
me ask you something though isn't this
also a theft on the Mexican people in
general the mere fact that we're talking
about the privatization of a company
that was once under the domain of the
public sector
introduce yourself I mean the bigger
picture here is that it's of course it's
not just oil and gas it's
lots of things that were once public are
becoming have become private and Mexico
under something called el pacto de
mejito or the pacto Mexico and so we're
talking about sectors wholesale sectors
are being sold off to private sector and
in this case
um the stuff with pemex or petroleos the
econos is extremely unpopular
relationships with the public polling I
think that about 70 of the Mexican
public is against this
and of course this has been something
that's been public for you know I guess
stay down at least for about a century
since 1917 I believe so yeah that's
definitely the broader picture uh for
sure
um I want to go back to the to the
emails uh because I know that's been in
the news a lot and and you know uh the
Democrats and then the Clinton backers
are saying that the Republicans are
making uh you know bipartisan hay with
this and it's really there's really
nothing to see here uh but the way some
of the things you've come across through
reading these emails which are now being
released as you said because of Jason
Leopold's uh lawsuit and we had Jason on
the show many years back I should
probably get him back on
um you found something interesting which
uh I I saw on Facebook about something
that Hillary asked to borrow uh just
just tell people what that is because it
sounded too ridiculous to to even be
true
I've done some backlash for posting that
on Facebook from some but basically it
was a a book an e-book I think about uh
at least it was an ebook
yeah it was an e-book about proper
maintenance of email and one of the
chapters uh in terms of like a how-to of
how to manage email one of the chapters
in the book was about
uh deleting emails and stuff and then
you know another part of that same
chapter was you know potential
repercussions uh legal repercussions of
deleting emails so it was like the fine
line of how many emails can one delete
without also potentially being uh you
know legally liable and so the backlash
I've gotten is that well this is a big
book about email maintenance and
management and one chapter and it was
about that topic but it it was you know
it's one of those situations where it's
like well what was the reason why she
was so interested in this book and also
uh you know uh I just you know I think
it just adds it was there's a story that
that said uh CBS News picked up and it
is interesting that that was in there
I'm not really sure if that was the
reason why she was interested in it but
it is clear that she
finds this stuff with email to be I
don't I don't think that it's it's
definitely not any sort of conspiracy
and obviously the right wing he's
interested in it for their own partisan
purposes but sure for those yeah for
those who care about transparency and
who care about integrity of the freedom
information act and who care about these
sorts of issues it's definitely uh very
troubling what she did of course there
were we've already seen that there's
been
uh you know newsworthy things in these
emails like stuff with International
Energy coordinator position and Other
Stories that'll come out of it that
clearly she didn't want out there and so
anything that stuff with email was is a
public relations problem from her
campaign but
um I might be asking you to speculate
here a little bit and let us know what
journalists are supposed to do but uh
what do you think is the reason that she
was using a private server and a
non-state department email account in
the first place I it has to it begs the
question
I think that um it gets what I was
saying I think that she uh she wants to
manage Her Image she wants to
keep a certain image of herself out in
the public that is not reflected at all
in the emails themselves and so I think
that her and her team thought that if if
she was managing the emails and the
server that they could
uh store things in a certain way and uh
you know I don't think there's a chapter
in the book I think that that's sort of
a coincidence but I think that that
coincidence does sort of ring true in a
way I think that this was the entire
purpose behind that private server and
the private email address and it's she's
definitely not the only person to ever
have done it but it doesn't mean that
it's less troubling to she she did it no
I think uh I mean the Obama
Administration which uh and I've
mentioned this on the air a couple of
times in the past as well one won an
award for transparency uh where where
the award was given at a ceremony that
was closed to the public
it just it begs uh it begs a lot of
questions uh and Steve we're out of time
I'm afraid but I really want to thank
you for for being on the show for
writing this piece and I encourage
people to go to a dsmog Blog which we
have a link to on our website that is
dsmogablog.com and we also have a link
to your article uh you're editor there
and I know you're going to keep working
on this and I'm now on your distribution
list so keep me posted as things develop
so we'll do thanks a lot for having me I
appreciate it thank you that was uh
Steve horn before him we had John
karianka who's a columnist with other
words uh before that he was uh CIA
counterterrorism officer and Senior
investigator for the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee and of course before
John we had egberto Willis who's still
with us in the studio Roberto thanks for
listening and joining and participating
and being part of the show it was fun it
was a pleasure it was honor uh we have
about two minutes or so left which is uh
hopefully plenty of time to tell you to
tune in every week of course and don't
forget to check Roberto's show out on
Thursdays at kpft at 3 pm for one hour
if you're listening uh in Internet land
and you want to join the conversation
for Alberto's show you can dial the
phone number for the station
713-526-5738 at any time uh between
three and four I guess you do you have a
specific window like 10 minutes in to
five minutes before the end or something
right and as soon as we but within seven
to ten minutes call-ins are probably
ready okay all right well the music in
the background lets us know that we are
pretty much out of time uh Emily thanks
for being here yeah two people had two
people hogging the mics instead of just
me this time uh of course uh uh Robert
our engineer thanks for um rolling with
the punches and and dealing with a
slightly unusual format this week
um want to encourage you all of course
to go to our website the
monitor.wordpress.com you can also go to
facebook.com monitor radio and you can
follow egberto on Twitter at egberto
Willis and you can also follow John
cariakou and Steve horn and me on
Twitter all of those links are on our
website and you can send an email to the
show anytime you like the email is the
monitor at journalist.com
I think that's all the time we've got so
uh goodbye and we'll see you next week
thanks for listening
foreign
[Music]
[Applause]